EMILIO MIGUEL BRUNA

University of Florida Dept. of Wildlife Ecology & Conservation & Center for Latin American Studies Gainesville, FL 32611-0430 USA embruna@ufl.edu +1 (352) 846-0634 www.brunalab.org @BrunaLab

RESEARCH & TEACHING INTERESTS: Tropical ecology and conservation, plant population ecology, plant-animal interactions, scientometrics and bibliometrics, science & science policy in Latin America

LANGUAGES: Native fluency in Spanish and English, Fluent in Portuguese

EDUCATION

2001	Ph.D. in Population Biology, University of California, Davis
1995	M.S. in Biology, University of California, San Diego
1994	B.S. in Ecology, Behavior, & Evolution with a minor in Literature, University of California, San Diego

PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS

2013-Present	Professor & Distinguished Teaching Scholar , University of Florida Department of Wildlife Ecology & Conservation & Center for Latin American Studies
2012-Present	Director , Florida-Brazil Linkage Institute, University of Florida Center for Latin American Studies, University of Florida
2020-2021	President, Association for Tropical Biology and Conservation
2013-2019	Editor-in-Chief, Biotropica
2014-2020	Board of Directors, Dryad Digital Data Repository
2007-2013	Associate Professor , University of Florida Department of Wildlife Ecology & Conservation & Center for Latin American Studies
2002-2007	Assistant Professor , University of Florida Department of Wildlife Ecology & Conservation & Center for Latin American Studies
2001-2002	NSF Minority Postdoctoral Fellow , Biological Dynamics of Forest Fragments Project Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia-Smithsonian Institution

AWARDS

2020	Selected for Induction into Alpha Zeta (Faculty Affiliate, UF Chapter)
2020	Roche Teaching Scholar, UF College of Agricultural and Life Sciences
2016	Sigma Xi (Full Member, University of Florida Chapter)
2014	Academy of Distinguished Teaching Scholars, University of Florida
2012	Outstanding Paper Award, US Chapter of the International Association for Landscape Ecology
2011	Graduate Advisor & Teacher of the Year, UF College of Agricultural and Life Sciences
2009	University of Florida Research Foundation Professor
2007	Julie S. Denslow Outstanding Article Prize, Biotropica & the Association for Tropical Biology & Conservation
2005	UF International Educator of the Year (untenured faculty category)
2003	Diversity Scholar, American Institute for Biological Sciences
2002	John L. Harper Early Career Researcher Award, British Ecological Society
1994	Ernest C. Mort Leadership Excellence Award, Revelle College, UC San Diego

FELLOWSHIPS

- 2012 Ciência Sem Fronteiras Special Visiting Researcher Fellowship, CNPq Brazil
- 2009 Fulbright Scholar, Brazil
- 2009 Visiting Researcher Fellowship, CNPq Brazil
- 2001 NSF Minority Postdoctoral Research Fellowship
- 2001 NSF International Research Fellowship (declined)
- 2000 Ford Foundation Dissertation Year Fellowship
- 1999 UC Davis Graduate Studies Fellowship
- 1998 UC Davis John F. Steindler Graduate Fellowship
- 1995 NSF Minority Predoctoral Research Fellowship
- 1993 Howard Hughes Senior Honors Thesis Fellowship
- 1993 UCSD Howard Hughes Summer Research Fellowship

RECENT GRANTS IN SUPPORT OF RESEARCH, TRAINING, & PROGRAM DEVELOPMENT (total >\$5.5 million)

- 1. Sloan Foundation. "Reinventing Field Courses" (\$74,060; PI: E. M. Bruna, Co-PIs: R. McCleery, P. Antonenko, N. Attias, D. Barton, 2020-2021)
- 2. National Science Foundation. SG: Synergistic effects of forest fragmentation and droughts on tropical plant population dynamics (\$199,904; PI: E. M. Bruna, Co-PIs: M. Uriarte, 2020-2022).
- 3. National Science Foundation. REU Supplement for "SG: Synergistic effects of forest fragmentation and droughts on tropical plant population dynamics (\$14,400; PI: E. M. Bruna, Co-PIs: M. Uriarte, 2021).
- 4. National Science Foundation. "The role of the matrix in fragmented landscapes: experimental tests and novel theory (\$525,000; PI: R. Fletcher, Co-PIs: E. M. Bruna, R. D. Holt, and B. Reichert, 2018-2023)
- 5. UF Informatics Institute SEED Funds: "Cross-National Patterns of Productivity & Collaboration by Latin American Scientists" (\$20,000, PI: E. M. Bruna, Co-PIs: Stephen Perz, Chris McCarty).
- 6. Mindlin Foundation. "Who are the Gatekeepers of Discovery? A crowdsourced project to ID & map the editors of academic journals" (\$3633, 2017-2018).

RECENT PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS, BOOK CHAPTERS, & ESSAYS (Total N = 105)

- 1. Mundim, F. M. E. H. M. Vieira-Neto, H. Alborn, & E. M. Bruna. *In press*. Disentangling the influence of resource variability and simultaneous attacks on whole-plant tolerance to herbivory. *Journal of Ecology* [PhD Thesis Chapter].
- 2. Bruna, E.M., R Chazdon, TM Errington and BA Nosek. 2021. A proposal to advance theory and promote collaboration in tropical biology by supporting replications. *Biotropica*, 53: 6-10.
- 3. Barbosa Silva, LV, HL Vasconcelos, MC Mack, AdS Ferreira, and EM Bruna. 2020. Effects of experimental nitrogen enrichment on soil properties and litter decomposition in a Neotropical savanna. *Austral Ecology* 45:1093-1102. [Ph. D. Thesis Chapter].
- 4. Brooks, ME, K Kristensen, MR Darrigo, P Rubim, M Uriarte, E Bruna, and BM Bolker. 2019. Statistical modeling of patterns in annual reproductive rates. *Ecology* 100 (7):e02706 [Ph.D. Thesis Chapter].
- 5. Bruna, EM 2018. Editorial board members are a non-random sample of ecological experts. *Nature Ecology and Evolution* 2(2):202.

SOFTWARE (N=1)

1. Fournier, A., F. Stevens, M. Boone, and E. M. Bruna. 2020. refsplitr. author name disambiguation, author georeferencing, and mapping of coauthorship networks with Web of Science data. R package version 1.0.0. https://github.com/ropensci/refsplitr

COURSE DEVELOPMENT & TEACHING AT THE UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA

Ecology and Conservation of Tropical Wildlife (Undergraduate, 03,05,07,11,12,14,18)

Data Collection & Management for Latin American Studies (Graduate, 2019)

Plant-Animal Interactions (Graduate, 2004, 2006, 2008, 2010)

Fundraising for Tropical Conservation & Development (Graduate, 2013, 2016, 2018, 2020)

Scientific Publishing (Graduate, 2014, 2015, 2017, 2018)

Ecological Principles for Development & Conservation Professionals (Graduate, 2010, 2011, 2012)

Tropical Forest Community Ecology (Graduate, 2000)

Design and Methods of Research in Latin American Studies (Graduate, 2008, 2010)

Research Methods in Tropical Conservation & Development (Graduate, 2003-2007)

Seminar in Wildlife Ecology and Conservation (Graduate, 2003, 2004)

Social Media Workshop (Graduate, 2016)

GRADUATE STUDENTS ADVISED AS COMMITTEE CHAIR

Thomas Smith	UF	Wildlife Ecology & Conservation	Ph.D.	In progress
Simon Parsons	UF	Latin American Studies	M.A.	2018
Ernane H. M. Vieira Neto	UF	Wildlife Ecology & Conservation	Ph.D.	2016
Fabiane Moreira Mundim	UF	Wildlife Ecology & Conservation	Ph.D.	2016
Ana Ceclia Silva	UF	Latin American Studies	M.A.	2014
Paulo Rubim	UFSCar (Brazil)	Ecology	Ph.D.	2014
Pedro B. de Vasconcelos	UFU (Brazil)	Biology	M.S.	2012
Christine Lucas	UF	Wildlife Ecology & Conservation	Ph.D.	2011
Cris Follman Jurinitz	USP (Brazil)	Ecology	Ph.D.	2010
Stella Copeland	UF	Wildlife Ecology & Conservation	M.S.	2009
Gwen lacona	UF	Wildlife Ecology & Conservation	M.S.	2008
Alana Vaz Ferreira	UFU (Brazil)	Ecology & Nat. Res. Cons.	M.S.	2008
lan Fiske	UF	Wildlife Ecology & Conservation	M.S.	2006
Matthew Trager	UF	Interdisciplinary Ecology	M.S.	2005
Maria B. Nogueira-Ribeiro	USP (Brazil)	Ecology	M.S.	2005

Students under my supervision have been awarded over \$35,000 in grants to support their research and been the recipients of prestigious fellowships and awards to support their studies:

- FLAS Fellowship (S. Parsons)
- NSF Predoctoral Fellowships (M. Trager, S. Copeland)
- UF IGERT Fellowship (C. Lucas)
- Inter-American Foundation Grassroots Development Fellowship (C. Lucas)
- UF Alumni Fellowship (M. Trager)
- Fulbright Fellowship (A. Neto)
- Science Without Borders Doctoral Fellowship (E. V. Neto, F. Mundim).
- NSF Doctoral Dissertation Enhancement Grant (C. Lucas)
- UF-WEC Jennings Scholarship (A. Neto, M. Trager, F. Mundim, G. Iacona)
- UF-CALS Doris Lowe & Earl & Verna Lowe Scholarship (C. Lucas, E. V. Neto).

Research by my students has also been recognized for its excellence:

- Fabiane Mundim: 2016 UF-WEC High-Impact Publication
- Ana Cecilia Silva: Honorable Mention, 2015 Charles Wood Thesis Award, UF Latin American Studies
- Fabiane Mundim: Honorable Mention, 2012 OTS Outstanding Paper Competition
- Christine Lucas: 2012 Marianne Schmink Award for the University of Florida's outstanding Dissertation in Tropical Conservation and Development.
- Ernane Vieira Neto: 2011 E. Lucy Braun Award (Outstanding poster presented at the Annual Meeting of the Ecological Society of America).
- Matthew Trager: 2005 Wildlife Grad Student Assoc. Outstanding Research Award (MS Category).